Guide to the John Morton Blum Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Morton Blum papers
1943-2011
MS 86
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.69
(19 boxes)
The papers consist of typescript drafts and research notes for three published works: Joe Tumulty and the Wilson Era; Woodrow Wilson and the Politics of Morality; and The Promise of America. Also included is some professional and personal correspondence.
Blum, John Morton, 1921-2011
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Morton Blum, 1966, 1985, 1991, 1994-1997, 2005, 2007, and 2009. Gift of Lewis L. Gould, 2016-2017.
Biographical / Historical
John Morton Blum (A.B. Harvard 1943, M.A. 1947, Ph.D. 1950) was a research associate, assistant professor of history, and associate professor at M.I.T. from 1948-1957. He has been a professor of history at Yale since 1957. Blum died on October 18, 2011, in North Branford, Connecticut.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by accessions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of typescript drafts and research notes for three published works: Joe Tumulty and the Wilson Era; Woodrow Wilson and the Politics of Morality; and The Promise of America. Also included is some professional and personal correspondence.
Historians; Blum, John Morton, 1921-2011; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory, Circa 1950-1966
  - Woodrow Wilson and the Politics of American Morality
    Scope and Contents
    Published version's title is Woodrow Wilson and the Politics of Morality.
    - Typed manuscript, pre-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - First draft, pre-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5-13)
    - Second draft, pre-1956 (Box 1, Folder 14-23)
  - The Promise of America; an Historical Inquiry typed manuscript, pre-1966 (Box 2, Folder 24-27)
  - Tumulty and the Wilson Era research notes on index cards, pre-1951 (Box 3–4)
- Additional materials, Undated; Accession 1986-M-001
  - Photocopies of Walter Lippmann letters, Undated (Box 1–3)
  - Steel, Ronald, research notes on Walter Lippmann, Undated (Box 4–6)
- Additional materials, 1929-1985; Accession 1991-M-073
  Related Archival Materials note
  Nine audio cassettes, with printed transcripts, on Civil Rights, 1963, originally from the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library, were separated from this accession and sent to the Historical Sound Recordings Collection, Yale University Library.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Received from John M. Blum, 1991.
  - "The Evolution of Anti-Poverty Policy," senior essay for the Yale College Dept. of History by Timothy P. Shriver, 1981 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Macroeconomic Education of John F. Kennedy," senior essay for the Yale Dept. of History by Thomas R. Burke, 1985 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Federal Government Deficits and Interest Payments As A Proportion of Gross National Product, 1929-1984:" statistical tables (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Material from John F. Kennedy Presidential Papers, President's Office Files: Presidential Transcripts
    - "Integration of the University of Mississippi", 1962 September 29-October 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Cuban Missile Crisis Meetings", 1962 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Tax Cut Proposals," vol. I, 1962 July 30-August 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Tax Cut Proposals," vol. II, 1962 October 2-1963 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Tax Cut Proposals," vol. III, 1963 August 13-August 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional materials, 1966-1993; Accession 1994-M-052
  Received from John M. Blum, 1994.
  - Professional correspondence, A-Z, 1966-1993 (Box 1)
- Additional materials, 1942-1994; Accession 1995-M-095
  Received from John M. Blum, 1995.
  - Professional and personal correspondence, subject files, 1942-1946, 1970s-1994 (Box 1)
- Additional materials, 1993-1996; Accession 1996-M-103
  Includes Accession 1997-M-075.
  - Professional and personal correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
- Additional materials, 1991-2005; Accession 2006-M-075
  This accession consists of general correspondence to John Blum arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Congratulatory messages on the publication of Blum's memoir, A Life in History (2004), and his New Haven- based murder mystery, An Old Blue Corpse (2005) are included.
  - Correspondence
    - A-D (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - F-L (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lilley, William, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - M (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - O-S (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr., 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Schorske, Carl, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Skidelsky, Robert, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - W-Z (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified, 1998 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Congratulatory messages
    - A Life in History, 2004 June-2005 November (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - An Old Blue Corpse, 2005 April-December (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Additional materials, 1986-2006; Accession 2007-M-052
  - Professional correspondence and publications, 1986-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional materials, 1989-2008; Accession 2009-M-069
  - Correspondence, general, 1998-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congratulatory retirement messages, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "From Rosie to Roosevelt", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Written introduction by John Blum to accompany the American Retrospective Series, National Video Resources.
- Additional materials, 2005-2011; Accession 2016-M-091
  This accession comprises correspondence between Blum and Lewis L. Gould, the Eugene C. Barker Centennial Professor Emeritus in American History at the University of Texas. The correspondence covers both professional and personal topics, including updates on scholarly articles in progress, feedback on scholarly articles, sports, and politics.
  - Correspondence from Lewis Gould, 2006-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Correspondence to Lewis Gould, 2005-2011 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Additional materials, 2011; Accession 2018-M-0014; 0.02; (1 box)
  This accession is one letter to Blum from Lewis L. Gould, the Eugene C. Barker Centennial Professor Emeritus in American History at the University of Texas.
  - Letter from Lewis Gould, 2011-05-13 (Box 1)